All right, בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*. Today we start on כ"ה עמוד
ב' *Kaf-He Amud Bet*. So we're half past the Hind. We pick
up where ירד לטבול *Yarad Litvol*, two lines from the top. So
the very top of כ"ה עמוד ב' *Kaf-He Amud Bet*.
And this is the משנה mishna *Mishnah* where it says that if
a person has a chance to go to the מקוה mikvah *Mikvah*,
this בעל קרי ba'al keri, *Ba'al Keri* who can't say שמע Shema,
*Shema*, if he can go to the מקוה mikvah *Mikvah* and get
out and dry himself off and get dressed, then he says before
sunrise, then he should do that. And if not, he should say
in the מקוה mikvah *Mikvah* and say the שמע Shema *Shema*, use
the water essentially to cover him to say the שמע Shema *Shema*.
So it implies that the end of the time of saying the
שמע shema, *Shema* is sunrise. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says. ירד לטבול אם יכול לעלות *Yarad Litvol Im Yachol La'alot*.
לימא תנא סתם כרבי אליעזר *Leima Tanna Stam KeRebbi Eliezer*? Let's say
the תנא *Tanna* is ruling anonymously like is basically implicitly assuming the
position of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*. Thank you. דאמר עד
הנץ החמה *De'amar Ad Hanetz HaChama*, that says שמע shema *Shema* can
only be said until נץ *Netz*, until sunrise. הנץ *Hanetz*. Thank you.
אפילו תימא רבי יהושע *Afillu Teima Rebbi Yehoshua*. No, it could even
be רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* who says that you have until three
hours into the day. דילמא כותיקין *Dilma Kevatikin*? Maybe the reason it's
emphasizing sunrise is because you're trying to do the ותיקין *Vatikin* way
of דאוונען davening *davening*. דאמר רבי יוחנן ותיקין היו גומרין אותה עם
הנץ החמה *De'amar Rebbi Yochanan Vatikin Hayu Gomrim Ota Im Hanetz HaChama*.
The ותיקין *Vatikin*, the, you know, the old ones, the ancient ones,
the scrupulous ones, they would finish the שמע shema *Shema* at right
before sunrise so that they could say שמנה עשרה Shmoneh Esreis *Shemoneh
Esrei* exactly at the moment of sunrise. So the emphasis of the
משנה mishnah *Mishnah* to do it by sunrise is not saying that
you won't be יוצא *Yotzei* after sunrise, but it certainly assumes that
saying it right before sunrise is the ideal זמן *Zman* and you
want to make that time. Okay. And now it continues. So there
you are in the מקוה mikvah. *Mikvah*. You don't have the time—shhh—you're
in the מקוה mikvah. *Mikvah*, you don't have the time to get
out and say the שמע shema *Shema* either before the end time
or before the ideal time. So you stay in the מקוה mikvah
*Mikvah*. The water serves as a cover for you. Your head is
outside of the water. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, let's take a
look at what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. So imagine the water
is like a type of a cloak over your body, like you're
wearing a toga with nothing underneath. That's how the water is serving.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying, ואם לאו יתכסה במים ויקרא
veyikra, *Ve'im Lav Yitkaseh BeMayim VeYikra*, so cover with water and read.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, והרי לבו רואה את הערוה libo
ro'eh et ha'ervah *VeHare Livo Roeh Et HaErvah*. How could you do
it? Your heart sees your nakedness. Meaning your heart in the chest
is in the—there's nothing dividing it and the genital area. And that's
a concern of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that the פסוק pasuk *Pasuk*
says ולא יראה בך ערבת דבר *VeLo Yera'eh Becha Ervat Davar*. This
is the implicit פסוק pasuk *Pasuk*, we quoted it before. No nakedness
should be seen among you that you cannot have an exposed nakedness
in the in the—when you are saying ברכות brachot. *Brachot* and תפלה
Tefilla, *Tefillah* and so on. So the question is, what does that
mean? Let's say it's not in the same space of my eyes,
it's covered, it's like under my you know, my neck below my
neck is covered, or maybe if it's exposed to any part of
my body that normally it's not exposed to. And that's what the
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* assumes, now it did—that's the way רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
explains it, that the emphasis on heart is because normally that area
is not exposed to the upper torso of the body. One does
wonder if it's also a sense of prayer and כוונה *Kavanah* and
there's a particular sense of the heart here. But this is a
major concern of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* which we actually rule that
one cannot דאוונען davening. *daven* or say ברכות brachot *Brachot* when it
is לבו libo? רואה roeh, את הערוה *Libo Roeh Et HaErvah*, when
there is nothing dividing, you know, the heart from the from the
genital area. There has to be some type of a belt or
some type of a garment or some type of—yeah, that's where the
גארטל *Gartel* comes in. So that's the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s concern. How
does it work if you're just covered straight with water? There's nothing
dividing. So אמר רבי אלעזר ואי תימא רבי אחא בר אבא בר
אחא משום רבינו *Amar Rebbi Elazar Ve'iteima Rebbi Acha Bar Abba Bar
Acha Mishum Rabbeinu*: במים עכורים שנו *BeMayim Achurim Shanu*. We are talking
about dirty water. Lovely idea that they would sometimes go in the
מקוה *Mikvah* in dirty water, but that would be a reality. A
מקוה *Mikvah* could be a well, you know, could have mud in
it and so on. דדמו כארעא סמיכתא *DeDamu Ke'ara Semichta*. That it
is like thick dirt. Meaning if you were like basically, you know,
your whole body
was you were up to your neck in dirt, so you wouldn't
say לבו libo, רואה את הערוה *Libo Roeh Et HaErvah*. It's like
every part of your body is clothed. It's not like there's an
opening, you know, it's not like
they're—one part of your body is exposed to the other part of
your body. So
שלא יראה לבו libo. ערותו *SheLo Yera'eh Libo Ervato*, so that the
heart does not see the nakedness. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan, *Tnu Rabbanan*:
מים צלולים *Mayim Tzulim*, if it's clear water, ישב בהן עד צוארו
ויקרא *Yeshev Bahen Ad Tzavaro VeYikra*. You can be up to your
neck in this clear water and say the שמע shema, *Shema*. So
again does not have the problem of לבו רואה את הערוה *Libo
Roeh Et HaErvah*. ויש אומרים *VeYesh Omrim*, some say, עוכרן ברגלו *Ocheran
BeRaglo*, that you have to, you know, get the water dirty with
your leg, meaning you're on a mud floor, so kick around the
mud to get the water dirty so it serves as some type
of a opaque covering. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, ותנא קמא
והרי לבו רואה את הערוה *VeTanna Kama HaHare Libo Roeh Et HaErvah*?
The first opinion that has clear water, what about the problem of
לבו רואה את הערוה *Libo Roeh Et HaErvah*? So קסבר לבו רואה
את הערוה מותר *Kasavar Libo Roeh Et HaErvah Mutar*. He's not of
the opinion that that's a problem. Okay, how do you define what
it means to be uncovered? I mean, you have to admit that
from our perspective, right, if you'd say, you know, you can't have
exposed nakedness, we would assume it means that other people can't see
it. Right, it doesn't matter. matter sort of that it's underneath your
from your neck down, it's all under the same garment, but the
גמרא Gemara so that's the opinion of the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
as long as it's not visible to the outside, it doesn't mean
that it can't be there's a problem of לבו רואה את הערווה.
libo roeh et ha'ervah. So the גמרא Gemara says הרי עקבו רואה
את הערווה, harei ikvo roeh et ha'ervah, what about your your heel?
עקבו, akvo, okay, what about your heel? That sees the ערווה. ervah.
Now why is that more of a problem than לבו? So רש״י
Rashi just says again, there's some assumption here that parts of the
body that are not normally exposed to one another have to be
covered. But again, it's a little unclear why if it assumes heart
isn't a problem, it assumes how about the heel? So the גמרא
Gemara. goes on to say the obvious answer, קסבר עקבו רואה את
הערווה מותר. kasavar akvo roeh et ha'ervah mutar. That's also permissible as
long as it's covered from outside view, it's not considered a exposed
ערווה. ervah.
But there's no issue about the fact that you're דאוונען Davening in
dirt? I mean, that you're I mean, is there any philosophical?
Well, that's a good point and we are talking about saying the
שמע, shema, not דאוונען. דאוונען does require a higher degree of comportment
and so on.
Right, and a lot of these things, the question is is about
what, you know, בדיעבד, bedi'eved, what counts, like the minimal requirements, you
know, if you have no other choice. But we are talking here
about קריאת שמע, Kriyat Shema, so that's a good point. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like
this, איתמר, itmar, it was taught, עקבו רואה את הערווה מותר. akvo
roeh et ha'ervah mutar. Now if you just exposed to your heel,
it's okay. And by the way, that's the way we rule. So
if a person is wearing some type of a thing from the
waist down with nothing underneath, that's actually not a problem. Okay, there's
only a problem of לבו רואה את הערווה, libo roeh et ha'ervah,
there has to be something at the waist level to divide, you
know, the upper and the lower part. But עקבו רואה את הערווה
akvo roeh et ha'ervah is not a problem. So the גמרא Gemara
says נוגע, noge'a, what about if your heel is touching your genital
area? Can you can you be saying the שמע Shema. in that
case? If your hand was touching, certainly not, but what if another
part of your body was touching? And you might remember when we
spoke about the two people under the bed in the same blanket
and so on, that there's a problem in addition to seeing, there's
a problem of touching. So what about the touching isn't by the
hand but another part of the body, is that a problem? So
אביי אמר אסור, Abaye amar assur, it's forbidden to say שמע Shema
or to or whatever, say ברכות. רבא אמר מותר, Rava amar mutar,
permissible. רב זביד מתני לה להא שמעתא הכי, Rav Zvid matni lah
leha shemaata hachi, רב זביד Rav Zvid taught this debate the following
way.
רבי חיננא בריה דרב איקא מתני לה הכי, Rabbi Chinana breih deRav
Ika matni lah hachi, the way we just said, רבי חיננא בריה
דרב איקא מתני לה הכי. Rabbi Chinana breih deRav Ika matni lah
hachi. נוגע, noge'a, when it comes to touching, your heel touching the
ערווה, ervah, כולי עלמא אסור, kulei alma assur, everybody agrees that's a
problem. רואה, if it's exposed to the ערווה ervah but not touching
it, אביי אמר אסור ורבא אמר מותר, Abaye amar assur veRava amar
mutar, אביי Abaye says it's forbidden, רבא Rava says it's permissible. Why?
לא ניתנה תורה למלאכי השרת, lo nitna Torah lemalachei hasharet, which is
a great line that the גמרא Gemara uses. It's funny like why
of all places it chooses to use it here, but we're not
angels. Angels maybe can can, you know, don't have to worry about
ערווה, ervah, but we can't. If you look at רש״י, Rashi, he
says, שאין להם ערווה, she'ein lahem ervah,
they don't have an ערווה, ervah, they can worry about these things.
אבל אנו שבשרנו יש לנו ערווה ואי אפשר לנו להישמר מכל זה,
aval anu shebasarenu yesh lanu ervah ve'i efshar lanu lehishamer mikol zeh,
you can't make such demands that are completely unreasonable based on our
human, you know, our human state. So therefore, I don't know, you
know, apparently if you're not living in a time where underwear is
necessarily always taken for granted, then לבו רואה את הערווה libo roeh
et ha'ervah could be a very common issue. How can you demand?
I mean not לבו, עקבו רואה את הערווה. akvo roeh et ha'ervah.
How can you demand that we never דאווען daven or say ברכות
or whatever in those scenarios? Also you have the גמרא Gemara very
often about you're under your blanket and you're naked and, you know,
it's too cold, you don't want to get out and get dressed.
So רבא Rava says you can't make those types of demands. תורה
Torah was not given for angels. So
והלכתא, vehilcheta, and the הלכה halacha is נוגע אסור, noge'a assur, like
רבא, Rava, touching is forbidden even with another body part. רואה מותר,
roeh mutar, being exposed is permissible for the for the heel. But
the הלכה halacha still is is that you cannot have the chest
and your genital area all, you know, all under the same garment
without there being some divider, some type of a belt.
There's an assumption here that at least your head is covered because
otherwise you wouldn't be able to say any of this?
What do you mean with a כפה kippah or something? No, that's
a totally later invention.
So there's no problem saying דברים שבקדושה devarim shebikdusha without covering your
head?
According to the גמרא, Gemara right, the גמרא Gemara had no idea
of a head covering. Right. I mean there's one אמורא Amora that
says he was so concerned whatever. Yeah.
So you're saying just a belt, a small thin belt is sufficient?
Assuming that you've got assuming a belt that you've got the area
is covered, right, that the genital area is covered and you have
a belt that, yes, that basically so that there's not it's not
right, a belt outside the garment.
Oh, but you could have another garment.
Right, meaning a belt that basically cinches the garment so that the,
thank you for clarifying that. No, no, no, right, I
did not mean a belt underneath. No, no, no, the point of
the
belt the point of the belt is that it cinches the garment
so that it's not it's not under the same space under the
same, you know, exposed space as the as the as the chest.
One quick question. Didn't we say yesterday if you cover you're lying
in bed and you cover yourself with a sheet? Yes.
Yeah, so that was either Assuming לבו רואה את הערוה is not
a problem
or
somehow that you were cinching the material around your waist. Okay.
And is there anything about underpants? Could that also?
Oh yeah, I mean for nowadays there's like no requirement for a
belt or anything, I mean,
even without talking about what's appropriate or not, but even if
somebody's just in their underwear,
right, that's enough, because of just the elastic or whatever. The Gemara's
case is that it was a straight material and there was nothing
cinching it at the waist. All right, so the Gemara says like
this.
Okay, and did we end up agreeing with
the
ערוה ervah or the ערוה ervah is a problem? No, ערוה ervah
was not a problem like the הלכה halacha of the Gemara. The
only problem is the לבו. So if you had it cinched at
the waist, even if there was nothing between that and the floor,
you would be okay, and between the outer garment and your body,
you would be okay. אמר רבא: Amar Rava: צואה בעששית tzoa be'ashashit
מותר לקרות קריאת שמע
כנגדה. mutar likrot krias shema k'negda. So we've completely left behind these
discussions. If you have a piece of excrement under a glass container,
you can say קריאת שמע krias shema in its presence even though
you can see it. ערוה בעששית ervah be'ashashit אסור לקרות קריאת שמע
כנגדה. asur likrot krias shema k'negda.
If there is an ערוה בעששית, ervah be'ashashit, one wonders what the
case is, but somebody is covered
with a transparent or translucent garment, so it's covered but it's still
visible, that remains a problem. Why? צואה בעששית tzoa be'ashashit מותר לקרות
קריאת שמע כנגדה, mutar likrot krias shema k'negda, צואה בכיסוי תליא מילתא.
tzoa bekisuy talya milta.
צואה tzoa is about being covered, because it says וכסית את צאתך,
vechisita et tze'atecha, as we're going to say, it speaks about the
Torah speaks about covering when you go outside of the camp to
take care of your business. והא מכסה veha michseh and it's covered
even though it's visible, which is interesting because if you remember yesterday
there was a discussion about not having it in your field of
vision. But that was when it was not covered.
So if it's uncovered, being able to see it is a problem.
But once it's covered, you're considered to have taken care of it.
So presumably you don't smell it though?
Right, exactly. ערוה בעששית, ervah be'ashashit, if you have a nakedness that's
covered with some clear covering, אסור לקרות קריאת שמע כנגדה, asur likrot
krias shema k'negda, that is a problem. ולא יראה בך ערות דבר
v'lo yera'eh becha ervat davar אמר רחמנא, amar rachmana, it should not
be seen, והא קמיתחזי veha kamitchazi and it's visible. Now of course
it's a little interesting because there's other reasons as well. I mean
if it's somebody else's body, so then there's a problem about הרהורים
hirhurim and sexual thoughts and so on. So and if it's your
own, well that's an interesting question. If you're by yourself, would that
constitute a covering? The discussion in the Gemara about being in water,
that seems to be transparent and it seems to be that it's
okay, although really most of the time if you're in water you
can't really see so well, if you try to look, if your
neck is up to water and look down, it depends, no?
Wouldn't someone raise the question of הרהורים hirhurim even if it's just
yourself?
No, that's generally assumed not to be a concern, I mean it
could be but that's generally assumed halakhically not to be a concern.
But anyway it is interesting that it says covering with something transparent
doesn't count and we just had the משנה mishnah about covering with
water. Anyway the Gemara continues.
אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: צואה כל שהוא, tzoa kol shehu, so again
we're still with this, if you have a little bit of excrement
like on the ground or whatever and it's in your presence and
you're trying to say שמע, Shema. and this could be like even
from animals and so on like we discussed the other day, מבטלה
ברוק. mevatlah berok. You just spit on it so that the spit
sort of overwhelms it, it's a tiny bit so the spit overwhelms
it, it's like it's covered. אמר רבא: Amar Rava: וברוק עבה, u'berok
avah, has to be a thick spit. Okay. אמר רבא: Amar Rava:
צואה בגומא, tzoa begumah, now let's say you've got it in a
little bit of an indentation in the ground, in a little pit,
מניח סנדלו עליה וקורא קריאת שמע. meniach sandalo aleha vekoreh krias shema.
You can cover it even with your own shoe, but right now
it's covered, you would be standing right above it, but it constitutes
being covered. Again we're assuming also presumably that there's not a smell
problem.
בעי מר בריה דרבינא, Ba'ei Mar brei deRavina, so Mar brei deRavina
asked: צואה שדבוקה בסנדלו מהו? tzoa sheduvuka besandalo mahu? They had this
problem even in the time of the Gemara. You have some stuff
on your sandal, on the bottom of your shoe, right? What's the
story? Maybe if it's all once it's sort of smushed, maybe it's
like covered because you're standing on the ground or something. Anyway תיקו,
teiku, so the Gemara doesn't know the answer. אמר רב יהודה: Amar
Rav Yehuda: But today what do
we
say?
I don't know. אמר רב יהודה: Amar Rav Yehuda: עכו״ם akum ערום
arum אסור לקרות קריאת שמע כנגדו. asur likrot krias shema k'negdo. If
you have a naked non-Jew, you can't say קריאת שמע krias shema
in his presence. So the Gemara says מאי איריא עכו״ם אפילו ישראל
נמי? mai irya akum afilu Yisrael nami? Why do you mention a
non-Jew? Even if it's a Jew you can't say קריאת שמע krias
shema in presence of somebody who's naked. So the
Gemara says ישראל פשיטא ליה דאסור, Yisrael peshita lei de'asur, for a
Jew it's obvious it's forbidden. Now by the way עכו״ם akum was
not the original גירסא, girsa, גוי goy or נכרי nochri was. נכרי,
nochri, what
is it in Steinsaltz? נכרי. nochri. Okay, but whenever it's עכו״ם akum
you know it's gonna be something a little unpleasant. Okay, because it
was self-censored to be עכו״ם akum and not נכרי. nochri. Anyway נכרי
איצטריכא ליה, nochri itztricha lei, you need to tell me that case.
מהו דתימא הא כתיב בהו ma d'teima ha ketiv behu אשר בשר
חמורים בשרם. asher besar chamorim besaram. There's a verse that says that
the flesh of donkeys is their flesh. So אימא כחמור בעלמא הוא,
eima kechamor be'alma hu, maybe it's like a donkey so you can
say שמע Shema, in front of a naked... farm animals, so קא
משמע לן דאינהו נמי איקרו ערווה, ka mashma lan deinhu nami ikru
erva, so it's teaching us that no, that they are also considered
to be an ערווה, erva, דכתיב ערוות אביהם לא ראו, dechtiv ervat
avihem lo rau, because we have the story by Noah that his
nakedness was called nakedness, so you see it is a issue. So
I really don't have anything to comment on that, I'll just say
that obviously there are some גמרות Gemarot that make some very, you
know, statements like this which question you know, should you know, reflect
attitudes about even the basic humanity of non-Jews, and there are other
גמרות Gemarot that are very much the opposite. So, but I really
have what?
Well, that's the problem, that's why, you know, there's whole issues about
teaching גמרא Gemara to non-Jews and that's why these things went through
self- a process of self-censorship,
because there are these very deeply disturbing in any in pretty much
in any religious tradition, you are going to define negative stuff about,
you know, about people who are not part of that tradition. I
would say that the, you know, the one sort of thing that
mitigates it is you have to also recognize that the Jews basically
were constantly being oppressed and persecuted by the surrounding hostile non-Jewish world,
so you know, you can understand where some of these things developed.
The problem is the question is not that it's there, but what
you I mean, well that is a problem, but the question is
what do you do with those things when they're there? You know,
how much do you say that this is like what the גמרא
gemara says, you know, or how much do you sort of see
this as an aberration and not as something that's representative of the
tradition? And that has a lot to do with interpretation, you know,
that's why we're still engaged in the process of תורה שבעל פה,
Torah She'be'al Peh, because we have a multi we have a text
that has multiple voices and the reader and the presenter has to
be the one that's going to interpret which of those voices is
dominant and which of those voices is, you know, is marginal, yes.
I just to point out someone with a flesh of a donkey
compared to Gentiles.
Thank you very much, right, exactly.
Well said, Charlie, yes. So now the גמרא gemara continues. It doesn't
solve the problem, but a bigger problem as Rivka is constantly reminding
us is how these גמרות Gemarot are learned and taught. You know,
it's the fact that it's there, if it's can be understood and
explained. The question is how much is it taught as authoritative lines
such as this and what that should dictate our, you know, our
attitudes. Yes.
But the same thing that goes on in the Chris- I mean,
what what we abhor that in Christianity that they do in terms
of the Jews, we're doing in our own way in terms of
Yeah,
no religion is free from it. You know, the question is what
do you do with those aspects of your tradition? Get rid of
it?
No, the
only mitigating factor yes, I understand.
But the only way
you
bracket
something is by diminishing its authority or you contextualize
it. In other words, there's no genre in any other religious tradition
like the oral tradition of the תלמוד Talmud which feels an absolute
freedom to enable us to put on the table every moment of
feeling and thought that has been reflected as part of the experience
of our people. It's the responsibility of the person who is an
authoritative decider to put it in its place and to say this
type of statement has to be made tiny and does not have
applicability of any authority in a particular context.
But I mean, but you know, I if your attitude towards the
תלמוד Talmud is it's holy, it's has
divine intent, divine thought, if you
really associate it with something very elevated and divine
and then there are all these completely unethical, immoral things like sex
with three-year-olds that we had yesterday, the people to whom it's not
presented, not bracketed, absorb it, it becomes part of their psyche and
it really, I believe, it affects the way they act in the
world and the way they treat each other.
I think that's right. I think we have to I think both
of those statements are absolutely correct. You know, so there are those
absolute dangers and we see them playing out, and it doesn't mean
that necessarily there's a problem with the תלמוד Talmud per se, it
means that there's a problem with how these things are being transmitted
and the cultures in which they're being transmitted.
Definitely problem with the תלמוד! Talmud! There's definitely a problem!
I
don't mean the line isn't problematic, I mean as a totality, yes.
First of all, this business about an עכו״ם Akum being compared to
a חמור chamor is a פסוק pasuk, in יחזקאל. Yechezkel. That's not
the גמרא gemara saying it. And second of all, it was only
a הוה אמינא havah amina of the גמרא.
Gemara, I understand, okay, but all right, yes. All right, let's move
on. Okay, I think we've said enough on this.
I'd also like to respond that that's not what the פסוק means
in פשט, pshat, the גמרא's Gemara interpreting it.
Okay, to be continued offline. ולא יתכסה לא במי משרה ולא במי
המשרה שיטול לתוכן מים. Velo yitchase lo bemei masra velo bemei hamasra
sheyitol letochan mayim. You cannot cover yourself with smelly water or water
for soaking flax which is smelly. until you dilute it with water
and it becomes less of a smell problem. So the גמרא Gemara.
says וכי כמה מיה רמי ואזי. V'chama maya rami v'azi. The גמרא
Gemara says I don't get it, you already got a lot of
water here. It's smelly. How much more gallons is it going to
take to get the water diluted? אלא הכי קאמר, Ella hachi ka'amar,
לא יתכסה לא במי הרגליים ולא במי המשרה כלל. Lo yitkase lo
bemei haraglayim velo bemei hamishra klal. These types of smelly waters, rancid
waters, or waters used for soaking flax, those are going to be
a problem, you can never use them at all because you can
put a lot of water in it and it will still remain
smelly. ומי רגליים, U'mei raglayim, but urine, remember that was something the
גמרא Gemara had less of a problem with, and it could be
very often that it wouldn't be as smelly as these things, עד
שיטיל לתוכן מים Ad sheyatil letochan mayim ויקרא,
if you add a little water to urine then that would be
okay. תנו רבנן, כמה יטיל לתוכן מים? Kama yatil letochan mayim? How
much water? כל שהוא, Kol shehu, even the smallest amount. רב זכאי
אומר רביעית, Rav Zakai omer revi'is, a רביעית, revi'is, which is like
three and a half ounces. אמר רב נחמן מחלוקת לבסוף. Amar Rav
Nachman machlokes levasof. That's all if you're adding the water at the
end, after the urine has been collected. אבל בתחילה, Aval betchila, if
it was in the vessel like the chamber pot beforehand, כל שהוא,
kol shehu, even the smallest amount. Why? Because רש"י Rashi says and
it's a little funny here that they use formal rules of ביטול,
bitul, of nullification, but if you have a little then as each
drop is coming in, it's being nullified by what's already there. But
of course it's a little funny because you would not assume that
this is necessarily a formal question about ביטול. bitul. Anyway, רב יוסף
אמר מחלוקת לכתחילה. Rav Yosef amar machlokes l'chatchila. So he says no,
the opposite. They debate at the beginning whether you need a little
bit or רביעית. revi'is. אבל לבסוף, Aval levasof, if it's already collected,
דברי הכל רביעית, divrei hakol revi'is, everybody agrees רביעית. revi'is. אמרי ליה
רב יוסף לשמעיה, Amrei leh Rav Yosef lesham'eih, רב יוסף Rav Yosef
said to his attendant, אייתי לי רביעית דמיא, Aisi li revi'is demaya,
go get me a רביעית revi'is of water. Presumably before he urinated
he said this, and then he wanted to דאווען, daven, כרב זכאי,
kerav Zakai, like רב זכאי Rav Zakai says that even at the
beginning you need a רביעית revi'is of water. Again, this was a
place where they did not have bathrooms and so on, so you
know, these... this was a very regular part of their life, of
their world. תנו רבנן גרף של רעי ועביט של מי רגליים, Tanu
Rabbanan garef shel re'i va'avit shel mei raglayim, if you have a
chamber pot, here one used for... for number two is called a
גרף garef and the one used for urine is called an עביט.
avit. But basically they are things used for collecting, you know, human
waste, אסור לקרות קריאת שמע כנגדן. assur likrot krias shema kenegdan. You
cannot say קריאת שמע krias shema in their presence. ואף על פי
שאין בהם כלום, Ve'af al pi she'ein bahem klum, even if they've
been emptied, you cannot say קריאת שמע krias shema in their presence
because they have A) what they're designated for and B) because you
know what they've been used for and they've absorbed smells and all
of that stuff. ומי רגליים עצמן, U'mei raglayim atzman, and as for
urine itself, עד שיטיל לתוכן
מים, ad sheyatil letochan mayim, until you put water in it. וכמה
יטיל לתוכן מים? Vekama yatil letochan mayim? How much? כל שהוא, Kol
shehu, a little bit. רב זכאי אומר רביעית, Rav Zakai omer revi'is,
a רביעית. revi'is. בין לפני המיטה בין לאחר המיטה, Bein lifnei hamisa
bein leachar hamisa, whether they're in front of the bed or behind
the bed, mean behind you. So again interesting the assumption that you
are saying קריאת שמע krias shema when you're in bed, right? That
was
a couple of places we've seen that so far. So even if
they're behind you, it's still an issue. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר
לאחר המיטה קורא. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer leachar hamisa korei. If
it's behind the bed you can read. לפני המיטה אינו קורא. Lifnei
hamisa eino korei. You can't if it's in front of the bed.
אבל מרחיק ארבע אמות וקורא. Aval marchik arba amas vekorei. You can
distance yourself four אמות amas from this. ורבי אליעזר אומר אפילו בית
מאה אמה לא יקרא עד שיוציאם או שיניחם תחת המיטה. Verabbi Eliezer
omer afilu bayis me'ah ama lo yikra ad sheyotzi'em o sheyanicham tachat
hamisa. Even if you have a room, not a house but a
room, a hundred אמות amas big, a huge room, if you're in
the same room with it, you cannot say שמע Shema. until you
either take them out of the room or put them under the
bed which is like you basically have buried them. איבעיא להו, Ibeia
lehu, היכי קאמר. heichi ka'amar. Now we're going to go back and
look at this ברייתא. braisa. What do we say? לאחר המיטה קורא
מיד, Leachar hamisa korei miyad, and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel says behind the bed it's okay. Does he mean behind
the bed you can read right away, meaning without anything else? לפני
המיטה מרחיק ארבע אמות וקורא, Lifnei hamisa marchik arba amas vekorei, and
if in front of the bed then it has to be four
אמות amas away from you? או דילמא הכי קאמר, O dilma heichi
ka'amar, maybe this is what he means. לאחר המיטה מרחיק ארבע אמות
וקורא, Leachar hamisa marchik arba amas vekorei, behind the bed is where
four אמות amas suffice. לפני המיטה אינו קורא כלל, Lifnei hamisa eino
korei klal, in front of the bed you can't read it at
all. So רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel then distinguished
behind the bed and in front of the bed. What is the
difference? Is it that behind the bed isn't a problem at all
or is it no, behind the bed four אמות amas works, in
front of the bed it's... it's never okay? תא שמע, Ta shema,
come and hear. דתניא רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר לאחר המיטה... Detanya
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer leachar hamisa... תא שמע דתניא רבי אליעזר
אומר, Ta shema detanya Rabbi Eliezer omer, לאחר המיטה, leachar hamisa, קורא
מיד, korei miyad, you can read right away. לפני
המיטה מרחיק
ארבע אמות, lifnei hamisa marchik arba amas, in front of the bed
you have to distance yourself four אמות. amas. So it's very clear
behind the bed is... is fine straight away and in front of
the bed it's enough that it's four אמות amas away from you,
not in your same space. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel omer, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says,
אפילו בית מאה אמה, afilu bayis me'ah ama, even if the room
is a hundred אמות amas big, לא יקרא עד שיוציאם או שיניחם
תחת המיטה. lo yikra ad sheyotzi'em o sheyanicham tachat hamisa. You cannot
say שמע Shema until they're out of the room or they're under
the bed which is like they're buried. So you see it's clear
that the position that distinguishes between behind the bed and in front
of the bed says behind the bed is okay completely, it's behind
you essentially, maybe there's even a bed dividing you in it, but
if it's in front of you and there's no divider then you
need four אמות. amas. But now the גמרא Gemara has another problem,
that the positions of רבי אליעזר and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel were the exact reverse in the second ברייתא braisa
than they were in the first. So גמרא Gemara says בעיא איפשיטא.
Baia ipshita. Okay, our question has been answered. We see what the
position of behind the bed and in front of the bed is.
if the exact reverse in the second ברייתא *Braisa* than they were
in the first. So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says בעיא איפשיטא *ba'aya ipshita*.
Okay, our question has been answered. We see what the position of
behind the bed and in front of the bed is. איפשיטא ליה
*ipshita lei*. מתניתין קשיא אהדדי *masnisin kashya ahadadi*. But the ברייתות *Braisas*
are still contradicting about who's רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* and רבי אליעזר
*Rabbi Eliezer* and רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* and רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*
are reversed in the two ברייתות *Braisas*. So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
איפכא בתרייתא *ipcha basraisa*, fine, reverse the names in the second one.
Okay, if you've got the exact reverse positions, one of them's got
to mixed it up. Then you have to figure out which one
has it mixed up. And that's the גמרא's Gemara *Gemara's* ask. How
do you know which one is wrong? מאי חזית דאפכית בתרייתא *mai
chazis d'afchis basraisa*, why did you reverse the names in the second
ברייתא *Braisa*? איפכא קמייתא *ipcha kmaisa*, how about reversing them in the
first ברייתא *Braisa*? גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, we have independent sort
of verification of who says these positions. So it says, איפכא בתרייתא
*ipcha basraisa*,
I just lost my place. מאן שמיע ליה דאמר כולי ביתא כארבע
אמות amos. דמי *man shamia lei d'amar kulei beisa k'arba amos dami*.
No, because the position that says even if it's in a room
a hundred אמות amos. *amos* big, it's a problem that it's in
the same room. That's a conceptual position that when you're in a
room, remember the whole idea of ארבע אמות arba amot *arba amos*
is it can't be in your space. So if you're outdoors, my
space is ארבע אמות arba amot *arba amos*. More than that isn't
my space. But if I'm indoors, any place in the room, I'm
in a room, any place in the room is in my space.
Conceptually, it's a position of כולי ביתא כארבע אמות amos. דמי *kulei
beisa k'arba amos dami*, the entire house, but here being room, is
all like ארבע אמות arba amot, *arba amos*. That's the idea, get
it out of the room regardless. So who is the one we
know says this position elsewhere? רבי שמעון בר אלעזר *Rabbi Shimon bar
Elazar* he, we know it's רבי שמעון בר אלעזר *Rabbi Shimon bar
Elazar* from somewhere else. And that was like the first ברייתא *Braisa*,
which is why we think the names of the first ברייתא *Braisa*
are correct. How do we know it's רבי שמעון בר אלעזר *Rabbi
Shimon bar Elazar*? אמר רב יוסף *amar Rav Yosef*, so if you
take a look, I'm sorry, רש"י Rashi, *Rashi*, so מאן שמיע ליה
*man shamia lei*, you see the רש"י Rashi *Rashi* is about fifteen
lines from the bottom, מאן שמיע ליה *man shamia lei*. We know
that this is the position of רבי שמעון בר אלעזר *Rabbi Shimon
bar Elazar*. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says לא lo. ידעתי היכן היא *lo
yadati heichan hi*. I don't know where the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
it says we know רבי שמעון בר אלעזר *Rabbi Shimon bar Elazar*
is of this position. So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says I don't know
where that is in all of ש"ס *Shas*. So if you take
a look at the גליון הש"ס *Gilyon HaShas* here, which is רבי
עקיבא איגר *Rabbi Akiva Eiger* at the bottom of the page, so
he says לא ידעתי היכן וכן ברש"י *lo yadati heichan v'chein b'Rashi*
and he now quotes you about fifteen רש"יs Rashi? *Rashis* in ש"ס
*Shas* where רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says the גמרא *Gemara* is referring to
another position somewhere else and I don't know what it's referring to.
So that's pretty impressive that there are, you know, you could listen
a number of times and you don't know what the גמרא *Gemara*
is talking about. So anyway, but that is, these are all the
רש"יs *Rashis* where he says לא ידעתי *lo yadati* what the גמרא
*Gemara* is referring to.
Yes,
are any of them resolved like by
תוספות Tosafot, *Tosafos*?
No, the, I mean, it's even more impressive
that
you're
right, that's the point. You know it all and you know it's
not really anywhere else. Every now and then תוספות Tosafot, *Tosafos* tries
to answer to find the place, but I say, you know, I
haven't gone through all of them, but I would say most of
the time it is that way that the גמרא *Gemara* seems to
be referring to another position that is not to be found elsewhere.
Takes it for granted. Right, well could be it wasn't recorded. You
also have to wonder, you know, different מסכתות *masechtos* were not all
edited by the same people at the same time. So maybe this
מסכתא *masechta* was referring to a reference it made somewhere else, but
you know, different schools of, so it wasn't all one editor that
put it all together.
I had a question. So our, our toilets today, would they be
considered
like a גרף של רעי *graf shel re'i*? We're going to get
to our toilets today, so hold on. Okay, so גמרא *Gemara* says
like this. Okay. אמר רב יוסף
*amar Rav Yosef*, בעי מיניה מרב הונא *ba'ei minei meiRav Huna*, they
asked רב הונא *Rav Huna*, מטה פחות משלושה פשיטא לי דכלבוד דמי
*mita pachos mishlosha pshita li d'k'lavud dami*. I said, look, it's obvious
to me that if the bed is less than three תפחים *tefachim*
from the ground, like nine inches, then it's like it's connected to
the ground. And if you put it under the bed, it's like
you buried it, this chamber pot. שלושה ארבעה חמישה שישה שבעה שמונה
תשעה מהו *shlosha arba chamisha shisha shiva shmona tisha mahu*? What if
it's anywhere between three to nine תפחים *tefachim*? It's act, and you
know, off of the ground and in the, and this chamber pot
is under it. Is that like it's buried or not like it's
buried? אמר ליה *amar lei*, so he says to him, לא ידענא
*lo yadana*. I don't know. עשרה ודאי לא מיבעיא לי *asara vadai
lo mibaya li*. Ten I didn't have any question about ten because
עשרה תפחים *asara tefachim* is already like it's, it's like its own
little, its own little hut or whatever. You know, something that's ten
תפחים *tefachim* off the ground makes its own space. So it's obviously
not like it's buried in the ground if the rise of the
bed from the ground is ten תפחים *tefachim*.
So גמרא *Gemara* says, אמר אביי Amar Abaye, שפיר עבדת דלא איבעיא
לך *amar Abaye shapir avat d'lo ibaya lach*. It's good you didn't
ask about ten תפחים *tefachim*. It's obvious ten תפחים *tefachim* if that's
the distance from the floor to the bottom of the bed will
not work. כל עשרה רשות אחרת היא *kol asara reshus achres hi*.
If it's ten תפחים *tefachim* off the ground, then under the bed
is like its own little room. So obviously
it's not going to be considered buried. So אמר רבא Amar Rava,
והלכתא *amar Rava v'hilchasa*, the הלכה halacha *halacha* is, פחות משלושה כלבוד
דמי *pachos mishlosha k'lavud dami*. If it's under three, it's like לבוד
*lavud* and it's buried. עשרה רשות אחרת היא *asara reshus achres hi*.
Ten is a different domain and it's like it's in its own
room, but it's not like it's buried. משלושה עד עשרה היינו דבעי
מיניה רב יוסף מרב הונא *mishlosha ad asara hainu d'ba'ei minei Rav
Yosef meiRav Huna*. From three to ten, that was the question רב
יוסף *Rav Yosef* asked רב הונא *Rav Huna*. ולא פשט ליה *v'lo
pashat lei*, and he didn't have an answer. Okay, so that was
just re... Okay, so that was just reframing what we just said.
אמר רב הלכה כרבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Halacha k'Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar.
We rule like רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar that
said anywhere that it's in the same room is a problem, even
if it's distant from you. Outdoors you can say four אמות. No,
anywhere in the same room is like it's within your four אמות.
Outdoors we go by four אמות. Indoors, same room, it's all like
it's in your space. וכן אמר באלי אמר רבי יעקב בריה דרב
שמואל Vechen amar Bali amar Rabbi Yaakov brei d'Rav Shmuel said it's
באלי Bali in the name of רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov the son
of שמואל's Shmuel's daughter, הלכה halacha כרבי שמעון בן אלעזר. We rule
like רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. רבא אמר אין
הלכה כרבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Rava amar ein halacha k'Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar. We don't rule like him. רב אחא אנסביה לבריה בי רב
יצחק בר שמואל. Rav Acha ansvei livrei bei Rav Yitzchak bar Shmuel.
Now רב אחא Rav Acha married his son off to the daughter
of the house of רב יצחק בר שמואל Rav Yitzchak bar Shmuel
ומרתא. u'Marta. אעיילו לחופה, Aeiyilu l'chupa, so they had their חופה, chupa,
they had the... ולא הוי מסתייע מילתא, v'lo havi mistayei milta, things
were not succeeding, which basically means they were not actually able to
have sex. Somehow they weren't succeeding in having sex on the wedding
night.
So, אזל בתריה לעיוני, azal basrei l'iyunei, so presumably, I don't know,
somehow he must have reported that to his father. So his, you
know, so he followed him to see what was going on.
חזא ספר תורה דמנח. Chaza sefer Torah d'manach. So he saw that
there was this ספר תורה sefer Torah in the bridal chamber, in
the room. אמר להו השתא לא אתי סכנתון לברי. Amar lehu hashta
lo asi sachanun livri. If I had not come, he said to
the father-in-law, then you would have endangered my son. Presumably, the bridal
chamber here was in the bride's father's house and he gave them
a room and in that room is where he happened to store
his ספר תורה. sefer Torah. So the groom's father said, if I
hadn't been here to check this out, then this would have caused
a danger, you know, to my son having sex in a room
where there's a ספר תורה. sefer Torah. דתניא, D'tanya, בית שיש בו
ספר תורה, bayis sheyeish bo sefer Torah, a house that has a
ספר תורה, sefer Torah, בית bayis in the גמרא basically means a
room. Okay? They did not have multi-room houses or whatever.
או תפילין, O tefillin, or there's תפילין, tefillin, אסור לשמש בו את
המטה, assur l'shamesh bo es hamita, you cannot have sex in the
same room, עד שיוציאם, ad sheyotziam, until you take them out, או
שיניחם כלי בתוך כלי, o sheyanicham kli besoch kli, or you put
them one vessel inside of one vessel and that vessel inside of
another. So basically, and he assumed that
if they were going to violate that,
then A, that's why they were having
problems and B, they could have
actually, maybe it was divine intervention that they shouldn't succeed so they
shouldn't be transgressing this. Otherwise, it would have endangered them, you know,
spiritually endangered them. In the room with the ספר תורה sefer Torah
basically? What? Hello?
So, אמר אביי, לא שנו אלא בכלי שאינו כלייתו. Lo shanu ela
b'kli she'eino kliso. When you do a one vessel in another vessel,
I mentioned this yesterday, right? One of them at least, ideally both,
at least one has to be not the normal vessel it's stored
in. Like if you have your תפילין tefillin in your תפילין tefillin
bag or the mantle over the ספר תורה, sefer Torah, that doesn't
really like cover it up. I mean, it does cover it up,
but it's seen as a part of it. So the reason for
a double vessel is like the thing is not here. You know,
it's put away, it's not here, it's not present. So at least
one of the vessels has to be the non-normal
pouch or covering.
אבל בכלי שהוא כלייתו, Aval b'kli shehu kliso, if it's their own
vessel, אפילו עשרה מני כחד מני דמי. afilu asarah mani k'chad mani
dami. Even if you have ten coverings, if it's all the normal
coverings, it's like it's not covered, it's like it's just one covering.
If you have your תפילין tefillin in your תפילין tefillin case, and
your תפילין tefillin thing, and in your תפילין tefillin bag?
Yes, correct, correct. אמר רבא, גלימא אקמטרא ככלי בתוך כלי דמי. Glima
a'kamtra k'kli besoch kli dami. If you have a cloak, you know,
in a place where books are stored, like a קמטרא, kamtra, well,
yeah, but like a ארגז, argaz, like a thing with a lid,
a chest, a chest where books are stored, that's like one, you
know, that's like a כלי kli inside of a כלי. kli. So
it's wrapped in the cloak and the cloak is in the, you
know, is in the bookcase. At least one of those has to
be, רש"י says the קמטרא kamtra is ארגז של ספרים argaz shel
sefarim is where the books are kept. So presumably it's the גלימא,
glima, it's the cloak they're wrapping it with, which is not the
normal thing in which it's kept.
All ספרים sefarim in this case? What does it mean?
Do you mean like ספרי תורה sifrei Torah as opposed to other
books?
Not a bag.
No, yeah, we're talking, it's not a codex, right? These are all
scrolls. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, דף
כה עמוד א, daf chaf hey amud aleph,
ספר תורה צריך לעשות לו מחיצה עשרה. Sefer Torah tzarich la'asos lo
mechitzah asarah. So we said it has to be in another room
or it has to be in a double vessel where one of
them is not the normal vessel. So he says, here's another solution.
You can make, you can divide the room, essentially put it in
a separate room. So if you make a wall עשרה טפחים asarah
tefachim high, like about three feet, then it's considered to be in
a separate room and that's okay. מר זוטרא איקלע לבי רב אשי.
Mar Zutra ikla l'bei Rav Ashi. So מר זוטרא Mar Zutra came
to the house of רב אשי. Rav Ashi. חזיא לדוכתיה דמר בר
רב אשי. Chazaya l'duchsei d'Mar bar Rav Ashi. So he happened to
go into the room of רב אשי's Rav Ashi's son, מר בר
רב אשי. Mar bar Rav Ashi. רב אשי's Rav Ashi son was
married. So this is interesting just in terms of giving you a
slice of life here, right before we saw that after the wedding
the groom and the bride, the bride and the groom went back
to a room in the
bride's parents' home. Here you're seeing that
after they got married or whatever were living together, at least in
this case they were living in the groom's father's home. So he
saw the room of מר בר רב אשי, Mar bar Rav Ashi,
ודמנח ביה ספר תורה, u'demanach bei sefer torah, that there was a
ספר תורה sefer torah in the room, ואביד ליה מחיצה עשרה ve'avid
lei mechitzah asara but it was behind a מחיצה mechitzah of עשרה
טפחים. asara tefachim. So presumably he was living with his wife in
this room in his father's house,
but the ספר תורה sefer torah was behind a מחיצה. mechitzah. אמר
ליה כמאן כרבי יהושע בן לוי? Amar lei keman k'Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi? Who are you ruling like? Like רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi that thinks that it's good enough to be behind
a מחיצה? mechitzah? אימת אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי? Eimat amar Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi? When did רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi say that's enough? דלית ליה ביתא אחרינא, deleis lei beita achrina,
that you don't have a choice, you don't have any other room
to put it in. מר אית ליה ביתא אחרינא, Mar is lei
beita achrina, you have another room to put it in. So you
shouldn't just be relying on this. אמר ליה לאו אדעתאי. Amar lei
lav adatai. He said back then, I wasn't thinking. Good point. So
if you take a look at תוספות, ספר תורה עושה לו מחיצה,
sefer torah oseh lo mechitzah, the little תוספות, he says ודוקא ספר
תורה. ve'davka sefer torah. All of this is discussion about a Torah
scroll, or we mentioned
תפילין, tefillin, things that have real קדושה kedushah like a Torah scroll
and
תפילין. tefillin. אבל בחומשים יש להחמיר כמו בספר תורה. Aval bechumashim yesh
l'hachmir k'mo b'sefer torah. If you have a חומש, chumash, right, like
a codex or something, then, you know,
this was before the period of printing presses, so even his חומש
chumash was handwritten. Okay, he said you should be strict. אבל בשאר
ספרים די בכיסוי בעלמא. Aval b'shar sefarim dai b'chisui b'alma. Other books
it's enough to have just one simple covering, you don't need a
double covering and so on. And this becomes all issue about, yeah,
well that's a question in general where which category are חומשים chumashim
today go into, they probably go into the שאר ספרים shar sefarim
category. But that becomes an issue about, especially in these Manhattan apartments
and not enough place to put everything, and what do you do
with your books and if you have to keep some of your
ספרים sefarim in your bedroom and so on. So one covering is
enough at least and just, and what if you had a glass
covering? Whatever it was, like one of those bookcases that has the
glass doors. Anyway, those are some of those הלכות. halachot. Now, כמה
ירחיק מן הצואה ארבע אמות? Kama yarchik min hatzoa arba amot? We
are not getting away from the צואה, tzoa, from the excrement. Okay,
so back to the משנה Mishna that says you have to be
ארבע אמות away from the excrement or from the smelly waters. אמר
רב אמר רב סחורה אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav amar Rav Schora
amar Rav Huna, לא שנו אלא לאחוריו. lo shanu ela l'achorav. Similar
to discussions we had a minute ago, that's only but again questions
about which way it's placed. If it's behind you, ארבע אמות are
sufficient. אבל לפניו, Aval lefanav, if it's in front of you, מרחיק
מלא עיניו, marchik melo einav, it has to be out of your
field of vision. וכן לתפילה, Ve'chen l'tefillah, and the same thing for
שמע, for שמונה עשרה shemoneh esrei would be even more so, there's
higher demands by שמע, by שמונה עשרה. shemoneh esrei. איני והאמר רב
אפרם בר פפא אמר רב חסדא? Eini ve'ha'amar Rav Afram bar Pappa
amar Rav Chisda? Is that really true? Did we say that a
person can stand עומד אדם כנגד בית הכיסא ומתפלל, omed adam k'neged
beit hakisei u'mitpalleil, that didn't we say that a person can stand
in front of a בית הכיסא beit hakisei and daven? And per
se, you know, presumably it's within the ארבע אמות, it's certainly within
the field of vision, and we are assuming that that would have
the same status as actual excrement. So the גמרא says הכא במאי
עסקינן בבית הכיסא שאין בו צואה. hacha b'mai askinan b'veit hakisei she'ein
bo tzoa. There's no excrement in the בית הכיסא, beit hakisei, it's
never been used, or somehow it's been cleaned out or something. It's
never been used and therefore it's okay. איני והאמר רב יוסף? Eini
ve'ha'amar Rav Yosef? Is that really true? בית הכיסא שאמרו אף על
פי שאין בו צואה, Beit hakisei she'amru af al pi she'ein bo
tzoa, where that the problem of davening in the vicinity of a
בית הכיסא beit hakisei of a bathroom is even if there's no
excrement in it. ובית המרחץ שאמרו U'veit hamerchatz she'amru and a bathhouse,
which is a problem also because of the smells and all that,
אף על פי שאין בו אדם, af al pi she'ein bo adam,
even though no people are in it and are using it right
now. אלא הכא במאי עסקינן בחדתא. Ela hacha b'mai askinan b'chadta. Not
just a bathroom that the excrement has been removed, it's that it's
never been used. Never been used is different. If it was already
used, then it gets the status as a bathroom as we said
before, once it's used. But if it's just been designated and not
used, then it doesn't really have a status. So the גמרא says
והמיבעיא ליה לרבינא? ve'ha'mibaya lei l'Ravina? But doesn't
רבינא Ravina ask הזמינו לבית הכיסא מהו? hizmino l'veit hakisei mahu? If
you designated it and have yet to use it, what's the law?
יש זימון או אין זימון? yesh zimun o ein zimun? Does your
designation, is that sufficient to give it the status or not? So
the גמרא says כי קמיבעיא ליה לרבינא למיקם ולצלויי בגוויה. ki kamibaya
lei l'Ravina l'meikam u'letzaluyei begavei.
His question was, can you daven right on the space that's going
to become a bathroom? They designated the space for the bathroom, maybe
they broke the ground, but they've yet to use it. So can
you daven right on the exact same space? There maybe the designation
is enough. אבל כנגדו, Aval k'negdo, if it's in front of you
and you're not on the space itself, לא. Then even if it
has a name of a בית הכיסא beit hakisei that's not a
problem. It's only a problem once actually it has been used and
you know those smells have been, have come there and so on.
So if it's not yet used, you can be in front of
you as long as you're not on the space, on the place.
And now very important הלכה finally wrapping this up, but very important
for us, אמר רבא הני בי כסאי דפרסאי, Amar Rava hani bei
kissai deParsai, the Persian bathrooms, toilets I should be saying, I mean
bathroom is a euphemism but you get my point, אף על גב
דאית בהו צואה, af al gav d'is behu tzoa, even though there's
excrement in it, כסתומים דמו, kistumim damu, it's like they are sealed,
it's not a problem. Why is this? If you look at רש״י,
Rashi, דפרסאי, deParsai, right before
the
משנה Mishna רש״י Rashi says the opening was, והוא בשיפוע vihu veshpua
and it was at an angle, והרי מתגלגל ונופל לגומא, vaharei mitgalgel
venofel laguma, and the excrement would roll away and into the pit
which would be not directly under where you were. So where you
were, there were no smells. So that was before they had all
that blue stuff that they put in the porta-potties or whatever. So
this basically is relevant because our bathrooms are essentially like this. Nothing
remains, the smells all get washed away right away and so on,
and therefore our bathrooms really do not have any of the status
of בית הכסא beit hakisei that's being discussed by the גמרא, unless
it's like a public restroom and then you've got, I'm serious, because
then smell and you've got all the other problems.
Now what is it for ד' אמות daled amot behind you and,
we're not,
I'm not going to get into it although there's too much debate
about the specifics of it. But גומא guma is a hole.
But what is it like on El Al planes, you know?
Right, so don't, if you want to actually דאוון daven in the
actual toilet itself, in the actual, this entire little room, I'm just
kidding. Okay, זב שראה קרי ונדה שפלטה שכבת זרע. zav shera'ah keri
veniddah shepaltah shichvat zera. We need one more משנה Mishna to get
us back to בעל קרי, ba'al keri although the entire emphasis about
the בעל קרי ba'al keri. had been the man, this משנה Mishna,
introduces the woman in sort of a very, as making an indirect
point, that even if you're already טמא, tamei, if you then have
the seminal emission, it's still a problem in this whole issue about
saying שמע. So a man who is already a זב, zav, we
quoted this before, who then had a seminal emission, or נדה שפלטה
שכבת זרע, niddah shepaltah shichvat zera, a woman who's a נדה niddah
who had sex before she was a נדה niddah and now the
semen is coming out, והמשמשת שראתה נדה, vehamishameshet sheratah niddah, or a
woman that had sex presumably and the semen came out and then
she became a נדה niddah afterwards. So the first two cases they
were טמא tamei and then they had the זרע zera problem, and
in the third case first the זרע zera came out, the semen
came out, and then she became a נדה. niddah. All of these
צריכין טבילה. tzrichin tevilah. Although the טבילה tevilah won't do any good
for the other טומאה, tumah, they need the טבילה tevilah in order
that they could דאוון daven and say their שמע and so on,
all of those things about the בעל קרי. ba'al keri רבי יהודה
פוטר, Rabbi Yehuda poter, Rabbi Yehuda exempts. If you're already טמא tamei
anyway, it won't help for the other טומאה, tumah, don't bother doing
it for this. Okay, we quoted this all before, but again in
this side הלכה we are finding out that the laws about בעל
קרי ba'al keri apply to women as well after they've had sex
when semen is coming out of their body.
They have to say שמע.
A woman does not have to say שמע, she does have to
דאוון. daven. Now, it's interesting although the earlier משנה Mishna said women
are חייב chayav in תפילה, tefilah, if you look at רש"י, when
רש"י says where is it,
שפלטה שכבת זרע, shepaltah shichvat zera, there's some רש"י here, one minute,
oh no,
somewhere רש"י says אם באה להתפלל. im ba'ah lehitpallel. Where's the רש"י?
Oh yeah, the first רש"י on the משנה, וכן נדה אם באה
להתפלל שמונה עשרה, vechen niddah im ba'ah lehitpallel Shemoneh Esrei, if she
wants to דאוון daven שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. So I find it
interesting, באה להתפלל ba'ah lehitpallel suggests like she might not be, if
she is choosing to דאוון daven שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, which is
interesting because the גמרא before said, the משנה before said women are
חייב chayav in תפילה. tefilah. So anyway, could be just talking about,
but maybe he was also reflecting a certain reality that they didn't
always do it. Anyway, let's see the גמרא. איבעיא להו, iba'aya lehu,
they asked the question: בעל קרי שראה זיבה לרבי יהודה מהו? ba'al
keri shera'ah zivah leRabbi Yehuda mahu? Let's say first the man became
a בעל קרי ba'al keri which obligated him to go to the
מקוה before דאוון davening and then he got the other טומאה, tumah,
then he got this זיבה zivah flow which made him טמא tamei
in another way. What do we say? כי פטר רבי יהודה, ki
patar Rabbi Yehuda, when is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda exempt? התם בזב
שראה קרי, hatam bezav shera'ah keri, when he started as being a
זב zav where טבילה tevilah wouldn't have done any good, and then
he became a קרי. keri. דמעיקרא לאו בר טבילה הוא, demei'ikara lav
bar tevilah hu, originally from that state מקוה would not have
helped. אבל בעל קרי שראה זיבה, aval ba'al keri shera'ah zivah, but
if the order was different, first he became a בעל קרי ba'al
keri and then he became a זב, zav, דמעיקרא בר טבילה הוא,
demei'ikara bar tevilah hu, when he was a בעל קרי ba'al keri
he was in the category of somebody who had to go to
the מקוה in order to learn תורה Torah or to דאוון. daven.
And then he became another status, maybe the original status remains. מחויב,
mechuyav, maybe he's obligated to go to the מקוה. או דילמא לא
שנא, o dilma lo shena, maybe it doesn't matter. תא שמע, ta
shema, come and hear.
והמשמשת שראתה נדה, vehamishameshet sheratah niddah, the woman who has sex and
then becomes a נדה, niddah, צריכה טבילה, tzrichah tevilah, needs טבילה. tevilah.
רבי יהודה פוטר. Rabbi Yehuda poter. והמשמשת שראתה נדה כבעל קרי שראה
זיבה דמיא. vehamishameshet sheratah niddah keba'al keri shera'ah zivah damya. It's exactly
the same idea. First she had the זרע zera coming out of
her body because, because the case where the זרע zera came out
after she became a נדה niddah was the first case. So this
case is the זרע zera came out first and then she became
a נדה. niddah. It's exactly analogous, that's like a man who first
had קרי keri semen and then became a זב. zav. וקא פטר
רבי יהודה, veka patar Rabbi Yehuda, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is
exempting. שמע מינה, shema mina, that is a good proof that when
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda exempts he exempts across the board even if
the order is reversed. תני רבי חייא בהדיא, teni Rabbi Chiyya behedya,
Rabbi Chiyya taught explicitly. בעל קרי שראה זיבה, ba'al keri shera'ah zivah,
if a בעל קרי ba'al keri who became a זב, zav, he
started as a בעל קרי ba'al keri and then he became a
זב. zav. צריך טבילה tzarich tevilah according to the חכמים, Chachamim, you
need to go to the מקוה. רבי יהודה פוטר, Rabbi Yehuda poter,
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda exempts. Once the man is a זב, zav,
the מקוה won't help so forget the בעל קרי aspect. הדרן עלך
מי שמתו. hadran alach mi shemeito. So that is the end of,
we're not done for today Rachel, but you can go. We are
going to actually start, that is the end of the three פרקים
perakim about שמע. Obviously there was a lot in that third פרק.
perek. Which was also about דאווענינג *davening* and the right space and
all those issues and so on. Now we move into a פרק
perek, *perek* which people really like. I assume people really like the
first three, but it doesn't have all of this stuff about the
various nakedness and so on and that, and it's about, this is
the fourth פרק perek. *perek*, we move from שמע *Shema* to שמונה
עשרה *Shemoneh Esrei*. Okay. And this פרק *perek* now focuses on the
דאווענינג *davening* on שמונה עשרה *Shemoneh Esrei* fully. Let's take a look
and get started.
Clothes or without clothes?
Right. No, that we've discussed already. All that is now behind us.
Okay. תפילת השחר עד חצות *Tefilat hashachar ad chatzos*. Now, we had
been talking about one of the times of saying שמע *Shema* and
in the night, in the evening and in the morning, now we
say one of the times of דאווענינג *davening* and we flip morning
and evening. The very first גמרא *Gemara* says this is a chiastic
structure, night morning, then morning evening. So now we're talking about the
time of דאווענינג *davening*. So when does the morning דאווענינג *davening* go
until? Until midday. רבי יהודה אומר עד ארבע שעות *Rabbi Yehuda omer
ad arba sha'os*, until four hours into the day. תפילת *Tefilat*—we're going
to see in the גמרא *Gemara* that רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* basically
uses a קרבן Korban *korban* model, and he says that the morning
sacrifice, the תמיד *tamid*, the morning communal sacrifice was only brought up
to ten hours into—up to four hours into the day, up to
10:00, not up to noon. And therefore תפילה tefillah *tefilah* also has
to end, has to be finished by that time. תפילת המנחה עד
הערב *Tefilat hamincha ad ha'erev*, afternoon דאווענינג *davening* goes until nightfall. רבי
יהודה אומר עד פלג המנחה *Rabbi Yehuda omer ad plag hamincha*, no,
until the half of the מנחה Mincha *mincha*, meaning we'll see, it
means basically an hour and a quarter before nightfall. He felt that
the afternoon communal sacrifice would only go until that time. So רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* assumes two things, as we'll see in the גמרא
*Gemara*. Number one is that the times of דאווענינג *davening* are based
on the model of the sacrifices, the קרבנות Korbanot *korbanos*. You could
doubt—you could debate that. And number two, that the times of the
sacrifices did not go until the entire noon or until the entire
all the way up to the evening, they ended beforehand. So he
assumes both of those. We'll see in the גמרא *Gemara* about what
the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* assumes. Now, תפילת הערב אין לה קבע
*Tefilat ha'erev ein lah keva*, evening דאווענינג *davening*, מעריב Maariv *Ma'ariv* does
not have any limit, you can do it the whole night. ושל
מוספין כל היום *Veshel musafin kol hayom*, and מוסף *Musaf* can be
the entire day. רבי יהודה אומר עד שבע שעות *Rabbi Yehuda omer
ad sheva sha'os*, there's a question whether there's a position here רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* that only allows מנחה Mincha. *mincha* until seven hours,
until one hour after מוסף *Musaf*—what did I say? מוסף *Musaf* until—until
one hour after noon. Now, תוספות *Tosafot* just points out that the
difference of the language of אין לה קבע *ein lah keva* as
opposed to מוסף *Musaf* is כל היום *kol hayom*. Let me just
double check תוספות *Tosafot* one minute.
Oh, no, he's—תוספות *Tosafot* has a different question. Why by מוסף *Musaf*
does it say כל היום *kol hayom* and by מנחה Mincha *mincha*
it says עד הערב *ad ha'erev*? And תוספות *Tosafot* says that there's
an obvious difference. מוסף *Musaf* can be done even in the morning,
it literally can be done כל היום *kol hayom*. And we know
that, sometimes, right, most of the time, you know, you דאווען *daven*
שחרית Shacharit *Shacharis* and, well, depends which שול *shul* you go to
and when the מנין *minyan* starts or whatever, but very often they
hit מוסף *Musaf* before, you know, while it's still day, while it's
still the first half of the day, before noon, and sometimes when
things שלעפ *shlep* on they even get מוסף *Musaf* after, you know,
in the afternoon, after—and therefore מוסף *Musaf* can be said at all
times. We'll find out later that when it comes at the time
of מנחה Mincha, *mincha*, really מנחה mincha, *mincha* is supposed to come
beforehand, but we'll worry about that later. So let's take a look
at the גמרא *Gemara*. רמינהו *Reminehu*, says the גמרא *Gemara*, I'll ask
you on this. מצוותה עם הנץ החמה *Mitzvatah im hanetz hachamah*. We
said before, we quoted a ברייתא *Baraisa* that says the מצווה *mitzvah*
of דאווענינג *davening* is at sunrise. כדי שיסמוך גאולה לתפילה ונמצא מתפלל
ביום *Kedei sheyismoch geulah l'tefilah venimtza mispallel bayom*. The מצווה *mitzvah* of—excuse
me—of שמע *Shema* is at sunrise in order that you should—one minute—juxtapose
גאולה *geulah* to דאווענינג *davening*, and the דאווענינג *davening* is first thing
in the day. So that assumes that the reason of ותיקין *Vatikin*,
there's a question, is the purpose of ותיקין *Vatikin* to get שמונה
עשרה *Shemoneh Esrei* right at sunrise or is it to get שמע
*Shema* right before sunrise? The general assumption, and תוספות *Tosafot* says it
sounds different ways in different places, is that the purpose is to
get שמונה עשרה *Shemoneh Esrei* right at sunrise. So you say שמע
*Shema* right before sunrise in order to be able to get שמונה
עשרה *Shemoneh Esrei* at sunrise because it comes right after שמע *Shema*,
which sounds like the time of saying שמונה עשרה *Shemoneh Esrei* is
right at sunrise, not the whole afternoon—not the whole morning. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says כי תניא ההיא לותיקין *Ki tanya hahi l'Vatikin*. That's
for the ותיקין *Vatikin* people. That's for the scrupulous people who want
to do it perfectly and do it like that. But הלכתא *halachically*
you can do it all the way until noon. דאמר רבי יוחנן
*D'amar Rabbi Yochanan*, because רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* said, ותיקין היו גומרים
אותה עם הנץ החמה *Vatikin hayu gomemin osah im hanetz hachamah*. The
ותיקין *Vatikin* would finish the שמע *Shema* with sunrise so they could
get שמונה עשרה *Shemoneh Esrei* at sunrise. Okay. וכולי עלמא עד חצות
ותו לא *V'chulei alma ad chatzos v'su lo*. So you're telling me
that everybody would agree that you can go until noon and no
further? Is that really true that you cannot say דאווען שחרית Shacharit.
*daven Shacharis* after 12:00, after noon? והאמר רב מרי בריה דרב הונא
בריה דרב ירמיה בר אבא *V'ha'amar Rav Mari breih d'Rav Huna breih
d'Rav Yirmeyah bar Abba*, did Rav Mari the son of Rav Huna,
the son of Rav Yirmeyah bar Abba say, אמר רבי יוחנן *Amar
Rabbi Yochanan*, saying in the name of Rabbi Yochanan, טעה ולא התפלל
ערבית מתפלל בשחרית שתים *Ta'ah v'lo hispallel Arvis mispallel b'Shacharis shtayim*. If
you forgot and you did not דאווען מעריב Maariv *daven Ma'ariv*, you
can do at—in the morning you can do two שמונה עשרה *Shemoneh
Esrei*s. שחרית Shacharit מתפלל במנחה שתים *Shacharis mispallel b'Mincha shtayim*. If you
missed the morning דאווענינג *davening*, שחרית Shacharit, *Shacharis*, you can do two
שמונה עשרה *Shemoneh Esrei*s at מנחה *Mincha*. So you see that even
if you missed it in the beginning of the day, you can
דאווען *daven* it in the afternoon. Obviously there's a difference; that's a
makeup, that's not the real time. Okay, but that's at least the
גמרא's phrasing, and the גמרא's now introducing us to this very strange
idea that we have nowhere else, and we will see in a
minute why at least by תפלה, tefilla that you have a makeup
period. Right, you never say, oh if you missed taking the לולב
Lulav on the first day, take it twice on the second day,
right? But here you have a makeup. So first the גמרא thinks
makeup really means that the time extends one extra period. So that
the גמרא puts a stop to. No. גמרא says כולי יומא מתיב
ואזיל, Kulei yoma mative azil,
so you see כולי יומא מתיב ואזיל, Kulei yoma mative azil, you
can דאוון daven the whole day. גמרא says here's the difference: עד
חצות יהיב ליה שכר תפלה בזמנה, Ad chatzot yeivlei s'char tefilla bizmanan,
until the midday you have the merit of דאוונינג davening in the
right time. That is the time of שחרית until noon. מכאן ואילך
Mikan ve-ileich afterwards, שכר תפלה יהיב ליה s'char tefilla yeivlei you get
the merit of דאוונינג, davening, שכר תפלה בזמנה לא יהיב ליה s'char
tefilla bizmana lo yeivlei you do not get the merit of דאוונינג
davening in the right time. Now even there it's not yet framing
it as a makeup. It's sort of like, okay you've gone a
little bit over but you're still דאוונינג davening שחרית. We don't frame
it that way, right? We say if you missed the time, you
first דאוון daven מנחה and then after you've done what the obligation,
then you do the makeup afterwards. The way the sense of what
it's saying here sounds a little not like that. Sounds like, okay
you missed the cutoff, but still do it, you still get you
know you can still keep on doing it. But we're going to
move into the other model which is the makeup model. You really
missed שחרית completely but now you have an opportunity to do a
makeup after. So now we're going to see where the גמרא where
this idea comes from that there is this makeup idea by דאוונינג.
davening. Let's take a
look. איבעיא להו: Iba'ya lehu: so they raised the question, טעה ולא
התפלל מנחה מהו שיתפלל ערבית שתים. Ta'ah velo hitpallel mincha ma-hu sheyitpallel
arvit shtayim.
We mentioned all of the cases of missing except missing מנחה. If
you missed מנחה can you do two מעריבס? Maarivs? What's the difference?
אם תמצא לומר טעה ולא התפלל ערבית מתפלל שחרית שתים, Im timtzei
lomar ta'ah velo hitpallel arvit mitpallel shacharit shtayim, I get if you
missed מעריב Maariv you can do two שמנה עשרה in the morning
משום דחד יומא הוא, mishum dechad yoma hu,
it's the same day, דכתיב ויהי
ערב
ויהי בוקר יום אחד, dechtiv vayehi erev vayehi boker yom echad, it's
the same halakhic day. אבל הכא Aval hacha but here, תפלה במקום
קרבן, tefilla bemakom korban, maybe תפלה Tefilla counts as a sacrifice, וכיון
דעבר יומו בטל קרבנו. vekhivan de-avar yomo batel korbano. Any sacrifice that
has to be brought on a particular day, if you miss the
day you can't bring it the next day. So if you missed
your דאוונינג davening of one day, you can't make it up at
מעריב because it's the next day. So this is the model of
a קרבן Korban, and this is setting the tone for pretty much
I'd say the major theme in the entire פרק, which is how
much is תפלה Tefilla about קרבנות Korbanot and therefore about like sort
of strict
formal you know sort of structure, and how much is תפלה Tefilla,
fundamentally like the גמרא said before, we discussed רחמי נינהו, rachamei ninhu,
about the human experience of prayer which is something that has no
real structure to it even if the structure is sort of add-on
later. So here the גמרא frames the more you consider it like
a קרבן, Korban you'll say okay maybe later in the day, sometimes
קרבן Korban, you miss the exact time when you're supposed to bring
the קרבן, Korban you can bring it later in the day, but
you can't bring a קרבן Korban on the next day. So the
גמרא says או דילמא, od dilma, or do we say כיון דצלותא
רחמי היא. kivan detzloota rachamei hi. This is exactly the dialectic of
the whole פרק. Is it קרבן Korban. or is it רחמי? Rachamei?
Is it like the objective detailed formal aspects of קרבנות Korbanot, or
is it more about רחמים, rachamim, about the you know about the
personal pouring out of one's heart and communication with God. So if
that's the core of תפלה, then כל אימת דצבי מצלי, kol eima
detzabei matzli, it's not about this day or that day, prayer is
something that fundamentally is at any time, there's no real time for
prayer. תא שמע Ta shma come here, דאמר רב הונא בר יהודה
אמר רב יצחק אמר רבי יוחנן, de-amar Rav Huna bar Yehuda amar
Rav Yitzchak amar Rabbi Yochanan, טעה ולא התפלל מנחה מתפלל ערבית שתים.
ta'ah velo hitpallel mincha mitpallel arvit shtayim. If you do not דאוון
daven מנחה, you have two
מעריבס, Maarivs, ואין בזה משום דעבר יומו בטל קרבנו, ve-ein bazeh mishum
de-avar yomo batel korbano, and that is not a problem that you
lost the קרבן. מתיבי, Meiteivei, I'll ask you on this: we say
מעוות לא יוכל לתקון וחסרון לא יוכל להמנות, me-uvat lo yuchal litkon
vecheisaron lo yuchal lehimanot, that if something that is perverted cannot be
fixed and something lacking cannot be counted. מעוות לא יוכל לתקון זה
שביטל קריאת שמע של ערבית וקריאת שמע של שחרית, me-uvat lo yuchal
litkon ze she-bittul kariat shema shel arvit ve-kariat shema shel shacharit, if
you miss the שמע in the morning or the evening you don't
get a makeup, you blew it. או תפלה של ערבית או תפלה
של שחרית, o tefilla shel arvit o tefilla shel shacharit, or you
missed מעריב or you missed דאוונינג davening שחרית, there's no makeup. So
here it says there's no makeup. וחסרון לא יוכל להמנות, vecheisaron lo
yuchal lehimanot, in ending the פסוק, if you lacked it you can't
count it. זה שנמנו חביריו לדבר מצוה ולא נמנה עמהם, ze shenimnu
chaveirav lidvar mitzvah velo nimna imahem, a group got together to do
a מצוה mitzvah and you weren't part of it, there's no you
can't make it up. Okay, anyway here you see no makeups for
דאוונינג. davening. אמר רבי יוחנן הכא במאי עסקינן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan hacha
bemai askinan, what are we talking about? שביטלו במזיד, she-bittlo bemeizid, if
you willfully did not דאוון daven during that time, then you don't
get make a makeup. אמר רב אשי
דייקא נמי דקתני ביטל, Amar Rav Ashi diyka nami dekatani bittel, it
says that you annulled, you negated, ולא קתני טעה, velo katani ta'ah,
you erred, שמע מינה. shema mina. So I just want to end
again by repeating this, that the conclusion as Michael indicated is we
live in a dialectic. If it was all about קרבנות, Korbanot then
there would be no makeup. There's no makeup by קרבנות korbanot, the
next day. If it was all about רחמי נינהו, rachamei ninhu, then
there would be no idea of any fixed time, and you wouldn't
need to say oh only the next day. Next time I can
make up, if I missed two times I can't make up, it
wouldn't even be an idea of making up, it's all רחמי rachamei
נינהו. ninhu. So the idea is that we actually תפילה is this
basically tension between these two models. It has the structure of קרבנות,
it has the formalisms, it has the times and so on, but
the רחמי, rachamei, which is at the as it was which is
at the foundation, allows for certain amount of flexibility. So it allows
for the fact that if you miss the right time, you can
do it again in the next time because at some level the
times really don't matter. Even for מנחה, the times really don't matter.
So we'll end here today.